Finding Aid for President (University of Michigan) records, 1967-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- SCHOOLS AND COLLEGES FILES
  - 2003-2004
    - Engineering, College of (Box 395)
    - Graduate School, Rackham
      - General (Box 395)
      - Board of Governors (Box 395)
      - Student Information (Box 471)
    - Information, School of (Box 395)
    - Kinesiology, Division of (Box 395)
    - Law School (Box 395)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (LSA), 2 folders (Box 396)
    - Medical School (includes self study report) (Box 396)
    - Music, School of (Box 396)
    - Natural Resources and Environment, School of (Box 396)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 396)
    - Pharmacy, College of (includes accreditation reports from the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education (ACPE)) (Box 396)
    - Public Health, School of (Box 396)
    - Public Policy, Gerald R. Ford School of (Box 396)
    - Social Work, School of
      - General (Box 396)
      - Personnel Information (Box 471)
  - 2004-2005
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, A. Alfred Taubman College of (Box 405)
    - Art and Design, School of (Box 405)
    - Business, Stephen M. Ross School of (Box 405)
    - Dentistry, School of (includes a DVD) (Box 405)
    - Education, School of (Box 405)
    - Engineering, College of (Box 405)
    - Graduate School, Rackham
      - General (Box 405)
      - Board of Governors (Box 405)
      - Student Information (Box 473)
    - Information, School of (includes a self-study report on the Masters of Science in Information program) (Box 405)
    - Kinesiology, Division of (Box 405)
    - Law School (Box 405)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (LSA)
      - General (Box 405)
      - Student Information (Box 473)
    - Medical School (Box 405)
    - Music, School of (Box 405)
    - Natural Resources and Environment, School of (Box 405)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 405)
    - Pharmacy, College of (Box 405)
    - Public Health, School of (2 folders; includes September 2004 Self-Study Report) (Box 406)
    - Public Policy, Gerald R. Ford School of (Box 406)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 406)
  - 2005-2006
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, A. Alfred Taubman College of (Box 416)
    - Art and Design, School of (Box 416)
    - Business, Stephen M. Ross School of (Box 416)
    - Dentistry, School of
      - General (Box 416)
      - Personnel Information (Box 473)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2036 ]
    - Education, School of (Box 416)
    - Engineering, College of
      - General (includes information on ABET accreditation visit in October 2005 a full set of self-study reports and the institutional profile prepared for this visit can be found in the President's Supplemental Files) (Box 416)
      - Student Information (Box 473)
    - Graduate School, Rackham, 2 folders (Box 416)
    - Information, School of (Box 416)
    - Law School (Box 416)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (LSA) (includes a DVD titled "LSA: Making the Difference in the Liberal Arts," 2005 Summary, Dean Terrence McDonald), 2 folders (Box 417)
    - Medical School (Box 417)
    - Music, School of (Box 417)
    - Natural Resources and Environment, School of (Box 417)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 473)
    - Public Health, School of (includes a CD-ROM: "Measuring Health Disparities") (Box 417)
    - Public Policy, Gerald R. Ford School of (Box 417)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 417)
  - 2006-2007
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, A. Alfred Taubman College of (Box 424)
    - Art and Design, School of (Box 424)
    - Business, Stephen M. Ross School of (Box 424)
    - Dentistry, School of
      - General (Box 424)
      - Personnel Information (Box 474)
    - Education, School of (Box 424)
    - Engineering, College of
      - General (Box 424)
      - Personnel Information (Box 474)
      - Student Information (Box 474)
    - Graduate School, Rackham
      - General (Box 424)
      - Student Information (Box 474)
    - Information, School of (Box 424)
    - Kinesiology, Division of (Box 424)
    - Law School (Box 424)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (LSA) (Box 424)
    - Medical School (Box 424)
    - Music, Theatre and Dance, School of (Box 424)
    - Natural Resources and Environment, School of (Box 424)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 424)
    - Pharmacy, College of (Box 424)
    - Public Health, School of (Box 424)
    - Public Policy, Gerald R. Ford School of (Box 424)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 424)
  - 2007/2008
    The individual files are organized alphabetically by unit name. Files include memoranda, reports and correspondence pertaining to such issues as faculty salaries, unit budgets, and curriculum/program changes.
    - Architecture and Urban Planning, A. Alfred Taubman College of (Box 481)
    - Art and Design, School of (Box 481)
    - Business, Stephen M. Ross School of (Box 481)
    - Dentistry, School of (Box 481)
    - Education, School of (Box 481)
    - Engineering, College of
      - General, 3 folders (Box 481)
      - Personnel Information (Box 514)
    - Graduate School, Rackham (Box 481)
    - Information, School of (Box 481)
    - Kinesiology, Division of (Box 481)
    - Law School (Box 481)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (LSA) (Box 481)
    - Medical School
      - General (Box 481)
      - Personnel Information (Box 514)
    - Music, Theatre and Dance, School of (Box 481)
    - Natural Resources and Environment, School of (Box 481)
    - Nursing, School of (Box 481)
    - Public Health, School of (Box 481)
    - Public Policy, Gerald R. Ford School of (Box 481)
    - Social Work, School of (Box 481)
- President's Supplemental Files 1967/68-2006/07
  The President's Supplemental Files series consists of material, frequently concerning major issues and initiatives of an administration, that were maintained in a filing system separate from the Topical File and the Schools and Colleges series. The Supplemental Files are organized by presidential administration and generally reflect the tenure of an individual president, but may include material from previous administrations.
  - Robben W. Fleming
    The Robben W. Fleming Supplemental Files subseries supplements material found in the Topical Files series for the years for Fleming's tenure. The Supplemental files series is organized into five sub-subseries: Budgets, Committees, Issues, Policies and Reports.
    - Budgets 1967-1981
      The Budgets sub-subseries is the best set of materials for studying Robben Fleming's reaction to the worsening financial climate in the 1970s. The records include letters, memoranda and reports, to and from President Fleming, university executive officers, state senators and representatives, and the governor. The files are arranged chronologically.
      - 1967/1968 (mostly re: Acts 124 and 240), 2 folders (Box 95)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 95)
      - 1970/1971 (includes some later material) (Box 95)
      - 1971/1972 (includes some later material) (Box 95)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 97)
      - 1974/1975, 2 folders (Box 97)
      - 1975/1976, 2 folders (Box 97)
      - 1976/1977, 6 folders (Box 97)
      - 1977/1978, 3 folders (Box 97)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 98)
      - 1979/1980, 2 folders (Box 98)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 98)
    - Committees 1967-1978
      The Committees sub-subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of committee, and includes committees both internal and external to the university. The majority of the committees represented are external. Although the folders often contain only reports and administrative materials, they provide evidence of the involvement of the University president in the wider fields of higher education and state and national government, and can be an important resource when studying the major issues of the various administrations. In examining Robben Fleming's reaction to student unrest and comparing it to that of other university administrators, for example, the researcher should examine the materials from the American Council on Education, Special Committee on Campus Tensions, and the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges, Committee on Student-Faculty Administration Relationships. Fleming's involvement in affirmative action policy-making can be studied from the files of the Federal Advisory Committee for Higher Education Equal Employment Opportunity Program (it should be noted that Fleming served as chairman for this committee), and from files of university affirmative action committees.
      - Committee memberships, declined or discontinued 1967-1978 (Box 98)
      - Access to Administrative Data Committee 1976-1977 (Box 98)
      - Affirmative Action Federal Advisory Committee 1975-1978, 8 folders (Box 98)
      - Affirmative Action Program (Box 98)
      - Advisory Committee 1977-1978
        - Director Search 1978 (Box 98)
        - Directorship Title Change 1978 (Box 98)
        - Review Committee 1975-1976 (Box 98)
      - Air Traffic Controller Career Committee 1969-1970 (Box 99)
      - American Arbitration Committee 1967-1975 (Box 99)
      - American Council On Education (ACE), Special Committee on Campus Tensions 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 99)
      - Anglo-American Conference (Ditchley Foundation) 1969, 1973, 2 folders (Box 99)
      - Ann Arbor Area Foundation 1968-1978 (Box 99)
      - Ann Arbor Public Schools Liaison Committee 1968-1973 (Box 99)
      - Association of American Universities (AAU), Committee on Graduation Education 1978 (Box 99)
      - Atomic Energy Commission, Labor Management Relations Panel 1968-1978, 2 folders (Box 99)
      - Beloit College Board of Trustees 1970-1978, 2 folders (Box 99)
      - Broadcasting, Committee on 1970-1976 (Advisory Committee to Michael Radock re: radio, television, etc.) (Box 99)
      - Buffalo State University Law School Board of Visitors 1968-1969 (Box 99)
      - Calendar Committee 1968-1978 (includes some earlier material) (Box 99)
      - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching
        - General 1973-1978, 3 folders
          - folders 1-2 (Box 99)
          - folder 3 (Box 100)
        - Presidential Search Committee 1977-1978 (Box 100)
      - Center for the Study of Automation and Society Board of Trustees 1969-1970 (Box 100)
      - Chrysler Corporation
        - General 1972-1978, 2 folders (Box 100)
        - Committee on Public Responsibilities 1973-1974 (Box 100)
      - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) 1970-1971 (Box 100)
      - Communications Committee 1977-1978 (Box 100)
      - Communications Media Committee 1966-1970 (Box 100)
      - Communications Review Committee 1973-1974 (Box 100)
      - Council for Financial Aid to Education 1969-1970 (Box 100)
      - Council of Ten 1968-1978 (Box 100)
      - John Deere and Company Board of Directors 1975-1978 (Box 100)
      - Detroit Public Schools-University of Michigan Liaison Committee 1968-1976 (Box 100)
      - Engineering Society of Detroit 1978 (Box 100)
      - Environmental Resources, Planning and Design, Committee on 1975 (Box 100)
      - Fee Committee 1973-1977 (Box 100)
      - Ford Foundation 1978 (Conference on Human Rights, Foreign Policy and the Media) (Box 100)
      - German American Conferences (Johns Hopkins University 1975 Hamburg, Germany, 1978) (Box 100)
      - Governor's Commission on Higher Education
        - 1972-1973
          - Agenda and Minutes (Box 100)
          - General, 3 folders
            - folders 1-2 (Box 100)
            - folder 3 (Box 101)
        - 1973-1974
          - Agenda and Minutes (Box 101)
          - General, 4 folders (Box 101)
        - 1974-1975
          - Agenda and Minutes (Box 101)
          - General (Box 101)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 101)
      - Health Services Committee 1974 (Box 101)
      - Honorary Degrees Committee 1971-1978 (Box 101)
      - Judiciary Committee 1970-1978 1970-1972, 6 folders
        - folders 1-4 (Box 101)
        - folders 5-6 (Box 102)
      - Law School Visiting Committee (Box 102)
      - Literature, Science, and the Arts Preparatory Committee 1969 (Box 102)
      - Michigan Economic Education Centers, Association of 1978-1979 (Box 102)
      - Minority Groups, Commission on 1971-1977 (Box 102)
      - National Archives Advisory Council 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 102)
      - National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges (NASULGC)
        - Committee on Federal Legislation, Committee on Legal Affairs 1974-1978 (Box 102)
        - Committee on Student-Faculty Administration Relationships 1968-1971, 4 folders (Box 102)
        - Executive Committee 1974 (Box 102)
      - National Commission on Accrediting 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 102)
      - National Committee of Arbitrators 1969-1978 (Box 102)
      - National Committee on Tax Justice 1969 (Box 102)
      - National Committee on U.S./China Relations, Inc. 1971-1978 (Box 102)
      - National Manpower Institute 1971-1978, 2 folders (Box 102)
      - National Movement for the Student Vote 1971-1972 (Box 102)
      - New York State Education Department, Advisory Council on Doctoral Education 1971-1974, 3 folders (Box 103)
      - Power Theater Dedication Committee 1969-1971 (Box 103)
      - President's Student Advisory Committee 1968 (Box 103)
      - Recreation, Intramurals, etc., Committee 1968-1969 (Box 103)
      - Resource Allocation, Commission on 1970-1973 (Box 103)
      - Rights of Privacy and Access to Information, Committee on 1977-1978 (Box 103)
      - Role Committee (Proper Role of the University of Michigan) 1968-1976 (Box 103)
      - Space Committee 1969-1972 (Box 103)
      - Steering Committee on Development of Academic Opportunities 1967-1968 (Box 103)
      - Strike and Boycott Policy 1970-1971 (Box 103)
      - U.A.W. (United Auto Workers), Public Review Board 1967-1973 (Box 103)
      - United Steelworkers of America 1973-1976 (Box 103)
      - University Council 1970-1978 (Box 103)
      - University Press Committee 1971-1973 (Box 103)
      - White House Conference on the Industrial World Ahead 1971-1972 (Box 103)
      - White House Conference on Youth 1970-1971, 4 folders (Box 104)
      - Women, Commission on 1970-1977, 2 folders (Box 104)
      - YMCA, University of Illinois 1968-1977 (Box 104)
      - Miscellaneous Organizations 1969-1978, 3 folders (Box 104)
    - Issues 1967-1978
      Arranged alphabetically, the majority of the Issues sub-subseries was created during the tenure of Robben Fleming's presidency and is the single best source from which to examine the student unrest which occurred during the Fleming administration. Of particular interest are materials under the following headings: Black Action Movement (BAM), Bookstore, Disruptions, Graduate Employees Organization (GEO), Open Meetings Act, and Vietnam. They are helpful in documenting what happened and how the administration responded. There are also interesting letters from alumni and the general public regarding the various incidents and actions taken by Fleming. The series contains materials on a variety of other issues as well and should be reviewed by any researcher studying the Fleming administration.
      - ADC Mothers (Aid to Dependent Children) 1968-1969 (Box 106)
      - Affirmative Action Program 1973-1974 (Box 106)
      - Affirmative Action-Title IX 1976-1978 (Box 106)
      - Autonomy, University 1971 (Box 106)
      - Black Action Movement (BAM) (see also "Disruptions")
        - General 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 106)
        - Black Student Center 1970-1971 (Box 106)
        - Responses 1969-1970
          - Alumni (Box 106)
          - General Public, 3 folders (Box 106)
        - Strike 1969-1970
          - General, 2 folders (Box 106)
          - Policies (Box 106)
          - Reactions
            - General (Box 106)
            - Alumni/Faculty, 2 folders (Box 107)
            - Michigan Legislators (Box 107)
            - Parents (Box 107)
            - Schools, Colleges, Departments, and other Academic Units (UM) (Box 107)
            - Students (Box 107)
            - U.S. Vice President Agnew, 2 folders (Box 107)
          - Student Petitions 1970 (Box 107)
      - Black Students 1967-1970 (Minority Groups) (Box 107)
      - Bookstore, Student
        - General 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 107)
        - Assessments 1970-1971 (Box 107)
      - Butterfield Theatre 1974 (Box 107)
      - Child Care Center 1969-1978, 5 folders (Box 107)
      - Classified Research 1967-1968 (Box 107)
      - Community Leadership Program 1968-1978, 8 folders (Box 108)
      - Disruptions
        - 1967-1968 (Box 108)
        - 1968-1969
          - Office of Student Affairs (Box 108)
          - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 108)
        - 1969-1970
          - General, 3 folders (Box 108)
          - Black Action Movement (BAM) Recruiting
            - General, 2 folders (Box 108)
            - Complaints and Kudos (Fleming), 2 folders (Box 108)
            - Hearings, 2 folders (Box 108)
            - Incidents
              - LS&A Building (Box 108)
              - South University (Box 108)
              - West Engineering Building (Box 108)
          - Bookstore, Student, 2 folders (Box 109)
          - Discipline (Box 109)
          - Huber Committee on Campus Tensions (Box 109)
          - Kent State University (Box 109)
          - Procedures (Box 109)
          - Recruiting (Box 109)
          - Research Paper (written by intern in the Center for the Study of Higher Education) (Box 109)
          - ROTC (Reserve Officers Training Corps) and Vietnam, Kudos and Complaints, 3 folders (Box 109)
          - Anonymous Responses (Box 109)
          - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 109)
        - 1970-1971
          - General (Box 109)
          - BAM (Black Action Movement) (Recruitment, Hearings) (Box 109)
          - Complaints and Kudos (Fleming) (Box 109)
        - 1975 (Sit In) (Box 109)
      - External Degree Program (Michigan Council of State College Presidents Survey) 1971-1972 (Box 109)
      - Freedom of Speech 1975-1977 (Box 109)
      - Graduate Employees Organization (GEO)
        - 1974-1975 (includes strike material), 3 folders (Box 109)
        - 1977-1978 (Box 109)
      - Institute for Defense Analysis 1967-1968 (Box 110)
      - Open Meetings Act 1976-1978 (Box 110)
      - Political Activity (Princeton Pause), 1969-1970 (Box 110)
      - Professorships 1967-1978 (miscellaneous University Professorships) (Box 110)
      - Research Libraries Group 1973-1978 (Box 110)
      - ROTC (Reserve Officers Training Corps) 1968-1970, 3 folders (Box 110)
      - Solar Energy Research Institute 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 110)
      - State Plan for Higher Education 1968 (Box 110)
      - Student Affairs (Student Services), Office of
        - 1967-1968 (Box 110)
        - 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 110)
        - 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 110)
        - 1970-1971 (Box 110)
      - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare
        - Affirmative Action
          - 1968-1970 (Box 110)
          - 1970-1971 (Box 110)
          - 1977-1978 (Box 110)
        - Title III 1971-1978 (Box 110)
      - University Facilities, Use of 1971-1978, 2 folders (Box 111)
      - University of Michigan, Flint Campus (Development), 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 111)
      - University Judicial System 1977-1978 (Box 111)
      - University Judiciary Committee, Permanent April, 1970 (Box 111)
      - Vietnam
        - Moratorium 1969 (Box 111)
    - Policies
      The Policies sub-subseries is arranged chronologically and contains correspondence, memoranda, official university statements and regents' communications, primarily from the Fleming years, pertaining to such topics as classified research, disruptions, draft resisters, plagiarism, recruitment, strikes, and use of automobiles by students. At the beginning of the file there is a master list of policy topics for each year. The file, therefore, is quite easy to use and because of the interesting nature of subjects addressed, is well worth review by the researcher.
      - Lists (Box 111)
      - 1967/68-1978/79, 12 folders (Box 111)
    - Reports
      The Reports sub-subseries is arranged alphabetically by originating unit or organization and consist of both university and non-university reports on a variety of interesting topics, including affirmative action, student roles in university decision-making, and enrollment of African-American graduate students.
      - Academic Planning and Analysis, Office of (Box 113)
        - "The Age/Rank Composition of the University of Michigan Faculty to 1995 A Simulation Study," 1975 (Box 113)
      - Affirmative Action
        - "Affirmative Action Program: The University of Michigan 1976-1980" 1977 (Box 113)
        - Affirmative Action Program Plan 1978 (Box 113)
        - Affirmative Action Study Committee
          - Report 1977 (Reorganization of the Affirmative Action Office, Commission for Minority Affairs and Commission for Women) (Box 113)
          - Report 1978 (Box 113)
        - Recruitment, Enrollment and Retention of Minority Students at the University of Michigan, Fall 1978 Report to the Regents on the, 1979 (Box 113)
      - Athletics
        - Committee to Study Intercollegiate Athletics for Women, Report 1973 (Box 113)
        - Organization Structure of Department of Physical Education and Athletics, Report 1967 (Box 113)
      - Coalition for the Utilization of Learning Skills, Review Committee Report 1976 (Box 113)
      - Energy
        - Energy, Office of, "Research Status Report: History, Activities and Achievements," 1979 (Box 113)
        - Paper Conservation Task Force Report 1974 (Box 113)
      - Ethics and Religion, Office of, Report of Evaluation Committee 1977 (Box 113)
      - Extension Service, Haber Report 1975 (Box 113)
      - Faculty Reform Coalition, Budget Task Force, Report 1971 (Box 113)
      - Financial Aid Office, "Some Characteristics of Students Receiving Financial Support from the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor Campus, 1974-1975" 1975 (Box 113)
      - Health Services
        - "Education for Health Services Administration at the University of Michigan," Task Force Report 1972 (Box 113)
        - Long Range Planning for the Health Service, Committee on, Report 1971 (Box 113)
        - Recommendations on University Hospital, Medical School and University Management of Programs in Allied Health Education at the University of Michigan 1976 (Box 113)
      - Literature, Science and the Arts, College of
        - "The Quality of the Freshman/Sophomore Academic Experience in LS&A of the Black Top-Achievers of the Class of 1980" 1978 (Box 113)
      - National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges (NASULGC), Committee on Student-Faculty Administrative Relationships, Statement (presented by R.W. Fleming, 1969) (Box 113)
      - Oceanography Review Committee Report 1977 (Box 113)
      - Opportunity Award Program
        - "Black Opportunity Undergraduates at the University of Michigan 1964-1970 A Retrospective View," 1971 (Box 113)
      - Periodic Health Appraisal Unit, Committee to Assess the, Report and Response to Report 1976 (Box 113)
      - Public Health, School of, Department of Population Planning
        - Report of Review Committee 1976 (Box 113)
        - Report of Consultant Reviewers 1977 (Box 113)
      - Public Policy Studies, Institute of, "Detroit's Leaders: A Preliminary Report," 1976 (Box 113)
      - Rackham School of Graduate Studies
        - "Black Rackham Graduate Students at the University of Michigan 1965-1970 A Retrospective View," 1971 (Box 113)
        - "Extending Opportunities for Graduate Study in Michigan: A Preliminary Report on the Feasibility of External Graduate Programs," 1976 (Box 113)
        - "Graduate Education" (Newman Report) 1972 (Box 113)